Frank G. Speck Papers 1903-1950 Mss.Ms.Coll.126
American Philosophical Society
Frank G. Speck Papers
1903-1950
Mss.Ms.Coll.126
American Philosophical Society
15.5 Linear feet
Anthropologist and ethnographer Frank Gouldsmith Speck was unique among Franz Boas' early graduate students at Columbia University. Unlike other ethnographers of his time who focused their studies on the Western Indian tribes, Speck chose to study the cultures of the Eastern Woodland Indians. Becoming the self-appointed salvage ethnographer for those tribes, Speck was regularly with the Indians he studied, collecting all aspects of their culture. The Frank G. Speck Papers consist of 15.5 linear feet of Speck's professional correspondence, field notes, lecture notes, and manuscripts of published and unpublished works. The material focuses on the Eastern Woodlands Indians, particularly the Catawba, Cherokee, Creek, Delaware, Houma, Iroquois, Labrador Eskimo, Mantagnais-Naskapi, Nanticoke, Penobscot, Powhatan, Algonkian, and Yuchi. The collection is divided into two subcollections: Subcollection 1 is comprised of Speck's research material and correspondence, and Subcollection 2 consists of his manuscripts and related correspondence. The two subcollections were acquired separately by the Society, and were originally cataloged as the Frank G. Speck Papers (572.97 Sp3) and the Frank G. Speck Manuscripts on Native Americans (970.3 Sp3p) respectively.
Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
Bibliography
Blankenship Roy, ed. The Life and Times of Frank G. Speck, 1881-1950. Philadelphia: Dept. of Anthropology, University of Pennsylvania, 1991. Call. No. B Sp35b
Related Archival Materials note
The American Philosophical Society Library contains several other collections from Frank Speck or that relate to him in some way. The collection of photographs and drawings (ca. 1800s-mid 1900s; ca. 5000 items) from the Speck papers have been removed and inventoried separately. The images are mainly from Speck's own collection, and focus on the United States and Canada, but there are also photographs concerning peoples of Mexico, South America, Africa, Asia, Australia, and Oceania. Additional Speck material includes the Speck Cherokee Collection (572.97 Sp3L) which consists of diaries, accounts, and medicinal texts in Cherokee collected by Will West Long and Morgan Calhoun, accompanied by notes by Speck and John Witthoft. In the material are several diaries kept by Long (mostly 1904-1917), records of the Gadugi (a Cherokee mutual aid group), accounts, records of births and deaths at Big Cove, and material collected on Cherokee botany by James Mooney in 1887. Several of the items contain information on Cherokee medicine, including formulae and curing charms. The Speck Catawba Texts (497.3 Sp3) concern myths, history, birds, reptiles, signs and omens, remedies, marriage, poverty, industry, food, charms, taboos, etc. The texts have both free and interlinear English translations. The Speck-Choate Photograph Collection (B Sp3c) contains photographs taken by J. N. Choate, a local commercial photographer in Carlisle, Pa. and collected by Speck. Typical images include "before and after" shots of students in native dress and school uniforms, the school band, and shots of the students at work in the saddle shop and making shoes. Choate also took a number of images of visiting chiefs in traditional dress, including the Lakota chief Spotted Tail, and the Cheyennes Man on Cloud and Mad Wolf. One photograph depicts Richard Henry Pratt seated with Quaker supporters. Among the tribes represented are the Lakota, Laguna, Cheyenne, Creek, Lipan, and Pueblo.
Other collections in the Library which relate to Frank Speck include the Franz Boas Papers (B B61), as well as Boas' other students Elsie Clews Parsons (Ms. Coll. 29), Paul Radin (497.3 R114), and Ashley Montagu (Ms. Coll. 109). Speck's colleagues are represented by the William Fenton Papers (Ms. Coll. 20), and the John Alden Mason Papers (B M384). The Library also holds the papers of some of Speck's students in the George S. Snyderman Papers (Ms. Coll. 51), Anthony F.C. Wallace Papers in the Wallace Family Papers (Ms. Coll. 64), and the Alfred I. Hallowell Papers (Ms. Coll. 26). Listings for additional Native American collections can be found in the online guide American Indian Manuscripts in the American Philosophical Society.
Outside of the Society Library, Speck material can be found at the University of Pennsylvania Museum Archives in the Frank G. Speck Papers. This 1.5 linear foot collection consists of correspondence and field reports dating between 1908-1950 for anthropological work with Indians of northeastern and southeastern United States, including the original manuscript for Penobscot Man
Other Finding Aids note
Freeman, John F. A Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society (Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1966) Call no. 506.73 Am4me v.65
Kendall, Daythal A supplement to A Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society (Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society, 1982) Call no. 506.73 Am4me v.65s
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Mrs. Frank Speck, 1950-1982, with additions by William N. Fenton, 1951, and John Witthoft, 1952.
Arrangement note
Subcollection I. Frank Speck Papers 1897-1950 10 linear feet
Subcollection II. Manuscripts on Native Americans 1913-1946 5.5 linear feet
Scope and Contents note
The Frank G. Speck Papers consist of 15.5 linear feet of professional correspondence, field notes, lecture notes, and manuscripts of published and unpublished works. The material focuses on the Eastern Woodlands Indians, particularly the Catawba, Cherokee, Creek, Delaware, Houma, Iroquois, Labrador Eskimo, Mantagnais-Naskapi, Nanticoke, Penobscot, Powhatan, Algonkian, and Yuchi. The collection is divided into two subcollections: Subcollection 1 is comprised of Speck's research material and correspondence, and Subcollection 2 consists of his manuscripts and related correspondence. The two subcollections were acquired separately by the Society, and were originally cataloged as the Frank G. Speck Papers (572.97 Sp3) and the Frank G. Speck Manuscripts on Native Americans (970.3 Sp3p) respectively.
Subcollection I is divided into several series. Series I came to the Library shortly after Speck's death in 1950 from Mrs. Frank G. Speck (with later additions from William N. Fenton and John Witthoft). Ninety-five percent of the material relates to North American tribes east of the Mississippi. The material was arranged by Anthony F. C. Wallace, and described in "The Frank G. Speck Collection" in The Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society (Vol. 95, pp. 286-89). According to Wallace, the Speck collection is an important ethnographic source material to those working on Eastern Woodlands Indian cultures since it constitutes a valuable body of unpublished data. In addition, the collection documents a significant chapter in the history of American science. As an early student of Franz Boas, Speck's work represents the first generation of American ethnographers to pursue the kind of research Boas encouraged and taught (a patient, detailed description of a primitive culture based on long and intimate residence with the community). Of particular interest are Speck's Columbia lecture notes from classes he took with Boas. Speck's field notes further indicate his method of study, in which casualness was itself unconsciously a technique for creating "rapport." Speck scribbled information on envelopes, scraps of paper, road maps, and old letters - in addition to ledger books and tablets.
When it came to organize the material, Wallace found the classification and ordering of the material to be "somewhat difficult." The collection could not be organized chronologically since Speck collected material over long periods of time prior to publication and did not date the material. It was also not feasible to organize the collection based on whether the notes were published or unpublished as it was not uncommon for Speck to have both types of information on opposite sides of the same piece of paper. Wallace concluded that a researcher consulting the Speck papers would be interested in a particular area or tribe, and would be familiar with the printed material on the subject. It was therefore decided to organize the material according to culture area, tribe, and community. The majority of this material has been described in John Freeman and Murphy Smith's Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian (1966) and Daythal Kendall's Supplement to Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian (1982). With the prominence of these two publications, it was decided to keep the initial organization and folder identification numbers of the collection when it was recataloged. Item descriptions from the Freeman/Smith and Kendall guides are designated with F&S and the entry number from the guide.
Series II of Subcollection I was initially labeled as biographical material, and organized separately in six boxes. This material arrived at the APS after Wallace had completed his organization in the 1950s. The series is predominantly correspondence to and from Speck regarding research topics, as well as other professional matters. When the collection was recataloged it was decided to reorganize it alphabetically by correspondent. Some of the items have been described in the Freeman/Smith and Kendall guides, the remainder were described when the collection was reprocessed.
Subcollection II was a gift of Mrs. Frank G. Speck, and initially housed at the Delaware County Institute of Science. The collection was eventually transferred to the Society in several accessions between 1971 and 1993, and processed in 1996 by Miriam B. Spectre and Timothy T. Wilson on a grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation. The collection is arranged in four series: correspondence, works by Speck, field notes, and photographs. Series II: Works by Speck, constitute the bulk of the material. At 4.5 linear feet, the series contains manuscript and typescript drafts, galley proofs, and page proofs of published and unpublished articles, reviews and books by Speck. The folders are arranged by title, with reviews being entered under the title of the book or article which is the subject. Series I: Correspondence contains four letters relating to publications by Speck, research material, Indian specimens, and Linton Satterthwait's summer research with John Alden Mason. Series III: Field Notes is one folder of undated material labeled "Delaware Social Dance Bustle", and Series IV contains four folders of photographs that appear to have been published by Speck.
Native American Images note
Native American Images note: A total of nearly 1,700 black and white silver gelatin photographs, sketches, albumen and photomechanical prints, negatives, and pictographs covering Speck’s fieldwork from 1904-1948 of Northeastern and Southeastern Native American tribes of Canada and the United States. Collected by Speck, except where noted, highlighted tribes include: Yuchi of Oklahoma, Algonquin of Labrador, Naskapis, Penobscot, Delawares, Iroquois, Houma, Catawbas, Cherokees, Creek, and Pamunkey. Images reflect the ceremonies and social customs of each, particularly, birch-bark containers, double curve design motifs, ceremonial masks and face paintings, utensils, clothing and hunting gear. Primarily textual material, the collection displays Speck’s unique use of image as a documentary tool. Arranged by tribe and region, each folder is cited in the APS Freeman Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian with references noted in the detailed inventory. Also, noted in Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches. Composition books, scrapbooks, pamphlets Miscellaneous clippings, 19 color photomechanical prints, 176 black and white photomechanical prints, 8 black and white illustrations, 21 newspaper clipping photographs, of Eastern Woodland, Plains, Great Basin, and Southeast tribes dating from 1922-1941. Collected by Speck for reference, the images are of portraits in tribal dress, dwellings, encampments, villages, pottery, masks, and weapons from various printed sources, such as, The Richmond Times and Metropolitan magazine. Not referenced in the APS Freeman Guide to American Indians. (Subcollection II)
Frank G. Speck Photograph Collection 572.97 Sp3, Film no. 1426 ca. 10,000 images, 1855-1950 Photographs Nearly 7,000 black and white silver gelatin photographs, postal cards, negatives, illustrations, sketches, engravings, paintings, cyanotypes, and albumen prints of the social life and customs of over 100 Native American tribes, primarily Eastern Woodland, dated from 1904-1950. Collected and photographed by Speck, with accompanying documentation in his papers (Ms. Coll. 126), the collection is noteworthy for its size, scope and quality. Gathered in the Franz Boas tradition, the images reflect group and individual portraits, clothing, ornaments, dwellings, weapons, utensils, ceremonies, hunting, fishing and trapping equipment unique to such tribes as: the Yuchi, Penobscot, Montagnais-Naskapi, Oklahoma Delaware, Cherokee, Ontario Iroquois and many Algonquin-speaking people. Other contributors include Frederick Johnson’s River Desert Algonquin, Vladimir J. Fewkes’ Catawba vessels, and V.M. Petrullo and John Mason’s Bororo Indians of Mato Grasso, Brazil. Of particular note, portraits as carte de viste, cabinet card, and tintype; oil paintings by Speck of a Pawnee camp, Plains Indian shield, and Cayuga longhouses. Arranged by tribe, each folder is noted with a reference number to its description in the Supplement to a Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian in the Library of the APS (1982). 13 boxes of Native American images of North and South America, 2 boxes of African, Asian, Australian and Oceania images. Table of contents available. (Subcollection I)
Lantern Slides 462 light-sensitive glass lantern slides (274 black and white; 188 hand-colored) of twenty Native American tribes dating from 1914-1938. Positive transparencies, 3 ¼” x 4”, of the social life and customs of tribes studied by Speck including: Catawba, Cherokee, Houma, Iroquois, Montagnais-Naskapi, and Yuchi. Some are educational, mass-produced dress portraits from the Seri, Beothuk, Eskimo, Seminole and Tuscarora tribes. Of interest, fourteen color slides of an unidentified opera noted here as “Indian melodrama.” Seventy-seven images depict landscapes, Africans, and Asians. Some, but not all, are referenced in the Supplement to a Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian in the Library of the APS (1982). 9 boxes. (Subcollection I)
Oversize The images are 39 photographs and 53 sketches dated from 1868-1941. Primarily portraits of such Native Americans as Sacajawea and Pocahontas with some stylized scenes by George Catlin, Seth Eastman, W. Gordon Fox, and L.T. Alexander. Collected or sketched by Speck, with emphasis on Eastern Woodland tribes. Of note, pastel and charcoal sketch of Iroquois false face, watercolor painting of a raised burial platform, a Harper’s Weekly print from 1868. Each image is referenced in Supplement to a Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian in the Library of the APS (1982). Basement and Sub-Basement. (Subcollection I)
Maps 65 printed maps and tracings annotated by Speck with ethnographic data on hunting territories and tribal boundaries of the Penobscot, Montagnais-Naskapi, and Catawba tribes dating from 1910-1930. (Subcollection I)
Film Naskapi scenes, ca. 1930, black and white, 16 mm, shot by Speck, shows the method of twisting rabbit skins for blankets; sleds with dogs; snowshoes; ice fishing; drums; and other aspects of social life and customs. 3 reels, no.520
Biographical/Historical note
Anthropologist and ethnographer Frank Gouldsmith Speck was unique among Franz Boas' early graduate students at Columbia University. Unlike other ethnographers of his time who focused their studies on the Western Indian tribes, Speck chose to study the cultures of the Eastern Woodland Indians. Becoming the self-appointed salvage ethnographer for those tribes, Speck was regularly with the Indians he studied collecting all aspects of their culture.
Although he spent the majority of his career in the field, Speck did not come from a rural background. Born in Brooklyn, NY on November 8, 1881 Speck spent the first seven years of his life in the city, a fragile and sickly child. As was common at the time, Speck's parents felt that a rural environment would be better for their son's health, and in 1888 placed him in the care of family friend Fidelia Fielding, living in Mohegan, CT. Fielding was a widow, a Native American, and the last speaker of her tribal language in New England. While with Fielding the seeds for many of Speck's professional interests were laid as she tutored him in nature, natural history, English literature, and Mohegan language and literature. At age fourteen Speck returned to his family, now living in Hackensack, NJ.
When Speck entered Columbia University at the turn of the century, he had not settled on a career - though he was leaning towards the ministry. That changed when he enrolled in a language course with the eminent linguist John Dyneley Prince. During the class Prince became fascinated by Speck's ability to provide first hand information on Native American languages long thought to be dead - particularly Pequot-Mohegan and Delaware-Mohican. Before graduating, Speck and Prince co-authored three articles. Prince also introduced Speck to anthropologist Franz Boas, who had begun his tenure at the helm of Columbia's anthropology department less then a decade earlier. Through Boas and Prince's encouragement Speck decided to pursue a career in anthropological linguistics, and after receiving his A.B. in 1904 started his graduate work under Boas. Speck was one of Boas' first graduate students and was one of a generation of anthropologists (along with Margaret Mead, Elsie Clews Parsons, Alfred Kroeber, Paul Raden, and Ashley Montagu) to learn and promote the Boasian approach to anthropology. Under Boas, Speck began his fieldwork among the Yuchi Indians of Oklahoma in 1904, receiving his M.A. from Columbia a year later. Speck initially planned to continue with graduate studies at Columbia with Boas until he was awarded a George Leib Harrison Research Fellowship from the University Museum of the University of Pennsylvania in 1907. Leaving Columbia for the University Museum, Speck received his Ph.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1908 and remained in Philadelphia for the rest of his career.
When Speck first arrived at Penn he was appointed as an instructor and assistant in general ethnology, working and teaching out of the Museum. Since the University did not have an independent department of anthropology at that time, courses were taught either out of the University Museum or the Department of Religion. During these early years Speck continued with his field work, which eventually put him at odds with the Museum's director, George Byron Gordon. Gordon wanted Speck to focus less on fieldwork and more on public and social functions important to fundraising at the museum. The feud between Gordon and Speck led to a number of incidents, including the confiscation of Speck's Penobscot manuscript (which was eventually published in 1940 as Penobscot Man). Finally in 1911 Speck was fired from the University Museum, only to be hired by the University as an assistant professor to replace Daniel Garrison Brinton. Two years later Speck became acting chair of the new Department of Anthropology, and chair in 1925.
It was not long after arriving in Philadelphia that Speck began his study of the Algonkians of the Eastern Woodlands. Speck went on to study the Algonkians of Delaware, the tribes of tidewater Virginia, the Cherokee in the Southeast, and the Iroquois, especially their ceremonialism. Speck's work among the Eastern tribes was indicative of his efforts to record dying languages and cultures. In many regards Speck was ahead of his time with his efforts to document the ways of life for relatively acculturated tribes, an idea which many anthropologists disdained. The eastern tribes had been overrun by European settlers during the Seventeenth and Eighteenth centuries and were largely destroyed by war, famine, and disease. Those who had survived were pushed westward and were absorbed by other tribes. As a result the majority of information regarding these tribes was historical not ethnographic. However, Speck viewed ethnology as a fluid field that was unlimited, and not a fixed study of past cultures. Further, he was never overly concerned with high-level generalizations or interpretations of his subject but focused more on recording well-attested facts. During his research Speck looked for variations that would turn up as he collected empirical data, and then would modify his original concept. To that end, Speck was not satisfied with providing a generalized picture of a tribe. He studied a tribe's language, technology, decorative art, myths and tales, religious belief, ceremonialism, social organization, music, and hunting territories. Speck also chose to focus on a tribe's link to nature, with ethnobiology, material culture, and uses of the environment playing major themes in his work.
Another integral part of Speck's fieldwork was collecting material culture. His love for collecting artifacts in the field was motivated by the special problems in which he became interested from time to time. Occasionally, Speck's interest in arts and crafts drew him within the borders of archeology. He would also have replicas made by Indians of objects no longer in daily use. Speck kept a number of objects in his office at the University, but most of the artifacts were sold to public museums, arriving heavily annotated as to their context within their culture group. Among the institutions to receive artifacts from Speck were the: Museum of the American Indian (now the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of the American Indian), American Museum of Natural History, Peabody Museum, Reading Public Museum and Art Gallery, Cranbrook Institute of Science, Denver Art Museum, National Museum of Canada, Royal Ontario Museum, Pitt Rivers Museum - University of Oxford, and Danish National Museum.
What made Speck successful in his research was the method he used in the field. Speck was a "bedside ethnologist," staying with the people all day, eating with them, learning their language, and sleeping in the village. This sense of ease and intimate form of fieldwork allowed Speck to gain the trust of the tribes, facilitating his collection of data. In fact, Speck was much more at ease among Indians, who were as much a part of his private life as his professional life than among Philadelphia society. He was rarely away from Indians for more than a month, going off to conduct field work when the opportunity presented itself, often without notice.
During the later years of his career, Speck began to study Iroquois ceremonialism. He felt that despite the vast material written on the Iroquois, very little was known about the diversity and characteristics of the cultures of the groups that made up the Six Nations. Also in his later years Speck was battling a failing heart and kidney disease, though this did not stop him from going into the field. It was during his trip to Red House, N.Y. in January 1950 to witness the Seneca perform their mid-winter rites that he became seriously ill. After returning to Philadelphia, Speck died at the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania on February 6 at the age of 68.